A Finding Aid to the Susan Cummins Gallery Records, 1984-2002, bulk 1990-2001, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Susan Cummins Gallery records
1984-2002
Archives of American Art
Susan Cummins Gallery
AAA.susacumg
Archival Resource Key
6.4 Linear feet
The Susan Cummins Gallery records measure 6.4 linear feet and date from 1984 to 2002, with the bulk of the records dating from 1990 to 2001. The collection sheds light on the California gallery's artists and operations through administrative records, artists' files, printed materials, photographic materials, audiovisual recordings, correspondence, and more. Also included are two files relating to art panels and lectures given by Susan Cummins.
Biographical / Historical
Susan Cummins Gallery was a contemporary art gallery established in 1984 in Mill Valley, California. The gallery was most well-known for its exhibition of American jewelry and other studio craft objects. In the 1990s, the gallery moved into a larger space and began exhibiting paintings and drawings as well. Most exhibitions held at the gallery were solo shows rotated monthly. Over the years, major artists shown at Cummins Gallery include Joyce Scott, June Schwarcz, Bruce Metcalf, Jamie Bennett, Dominic Di Mare, and Bob Ebendorf. The gallery closed in 2002. Group shows include Faceted Glass (1984)--the gallery's first show, Outcasts: Jewelry from Junk (1992), The Weight of Gold: Invitational Group Show (1993), and Jewelry as an Object of Installation (2001).
Susan Cummins was born December 27, 1946, in Minneapolis, Minnesota. Growing up, her family moved around to several states but mostly settled in the west coast. After high school, Cummins went on an American Field Service trip to Europe, and it was during her trip that she decided to study art in college. She attended Scripps College, studied under Arthur Stevens, and wrote her thesis on Rodin's relationship to dance. After college, Cummins moved to Washington, D.C. and struggled to find work in her field. She briefly volunteered at the National Museum of American Art and had worked for the Black Man's Development Center and a government lab before moving back to the west coast. She moved to Mill Valley and began running The Fireworks, a ceramics shop owned by a former college friend, Beth Changstrom. In 1983, Cummins and Changstrom took over the Horizon Gallery's space in Mill Valley and founded Beth Changstrom Ceramics and Susan Cummins Gallery. Throughout her tenure running the gallery, Cummins was close friends with some of her artists, especially Bruce Metcalf, Dominic Di Mare, and Bob Ebendorf. Cummins helped found Art Jewelry Forum in 1997 to promote and educate the collecting public about jewelry. She has served on the boards of the American Craft Council (2018 Honorary Fellow) and the Headlands Center for the Arts; she is the current director of the Rotasa Foundation.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as two series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1984-2001 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Artists' Files, 1984-2002 (Box 2-7; 5.9 linear feet)
Scope and Contents
The Susan Cummins Gallery records measure 6.4 linear feet and date from 1984 to 2002, with the bulk of the records dating from 1990 to 2001. The collection sheds light on the California gallery's artists and operations through administrative records and artists' files. Administrative records include group show exhibition files, gallery exhibition announcements, newspaper and magazine clippings, casette tapes, and papers from panels and lectures given by Cummins. Artists' files mainly consist of correspondence, resumes, exhibition announcements, articles about the artist, show reviews, and photographic materials. Some of the files include exhibition materials such as price lists, correspondence with other galleries and institutions, photos, and some sales records. Artists featured include Joyce Scott, June Schwarcz, Bruce Metcalf, Jamie Bennett, Dominic Di Mare, Thomas Mann, Keith Lewis, Bob Ebendorf, and Sandra Enterline.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 2003 by Susan Cummins, gallery founder and owner, as part of the Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Susan Cummins conducted by Jo Lauria, October 22, 2009
Art galleries, Commercial -- California; Jewelry -- Collectors and collecting; Painters -- California; American studio craft movement; Cummins, Susan; Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America; Metcalf, Bruce, 1949-; Scott, Joyce J., 1948-; Ebendorf, Robert, 1938-; Hu, Mary Lee, 1943-
- Administrative Records, 1984-2001; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Printed materials consist of clippings about Susan Cummins Gallery, the gallery's exhibits, artists, and other art-related topics, mostly concerning jewelry; and one catalog from the exhibition, Beyond the Obvious: Rethinking Jewelry (2000), held at the San Francisco Craft and Folk Art Museum and curated by Cummins. Group show exhibition files include two cassette tapes from Why Painting? (1992), and from The Weight of Gold (1993), artist statements, exhibition labels, correspondence, and price lists. Cummins's professional papers include lecture notes, transcripts, writings, and press releases. Susan Cummins' Panel and lecture files include transcripts, notes, reference material, and scant correspondence.
  - Bay Area Artists and Collections; Berkson, Sonnit, Parmenter, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition, Why Painting? (1992), circa 1992; Archival Resource Key; 2 Cassette tapes (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition,The Weight of Gold: Invitational Group Show (1993), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Solo Shows, circa 1984-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Group Shows, 1984-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Images of Artwork, 1997; Archival Resource Key; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material, 1989-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Susan Cummins, Panel, "Carried by the Current-Narrative Imagery", 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Susan Cummins, Panels, Lectures, and Notes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Artists' Files, 1984-2002; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 5.9 Linear feet Box 1-7
  Artists' files mainly consist of correspondence, resumes, exhibition announcements, articles about the artist, show reviews, and photographic materials. Some of the files include exhibition materials such as price lists, correspondence with other galleries and institutions, photos, and some sales records. Several audiovisual recordings from artists' interviews, panels, and exhibitions are also present.
  - Alepedis, Efharis, 2001-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Arleo, Adrian, Martha Holt, and Gail Caulfield; "Nature/Figure", undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassette (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Barnaby, Margaret, 1986-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Baum, Jan, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bean, Bennett, January 1990; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bennett, Jamie, 1997-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bennet, Jamie and Bob Ebendorf, Lecture, March 1990; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Browne, Kathleen, 1994-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Buszkiewicz, Kathy, 1996-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cathey, Stuart, 1995-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Class, Petra, 1994-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cooperman, Andrew, 1995-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cummins, Paul, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Da Silva, Marilyn, 1994-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Deal, Nancy, 1998-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dill, Lesley, 1996-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ebendorf, Robert, 1984-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Enterline, Sandra, 1988-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
  - Faulkenhagen, Diane, 1997-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Flynn, Pat, 1990-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Ford, Margaret, April 1993; Archival Resource Key; 1 Cassette tape (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fuller, Betsy, "Jewelry Stories", undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Cassette tape (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gilbert, Karen, 1997-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Gleason, Angela, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Goodman, Christina, 1995-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Granlick, Lisa, 1989-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  - Gray, Myra Mimlitsch, 1993-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Harris, Alfred, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Harvey, Mielle, 1999-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Heinrich, Barbara, 1988-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
  - Heinrich, Barbara, Photos of Artwork, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hu, Mary Lee, 1993-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
  - Hu, Mary Lee, Slides of Artwork, 1990s-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Iversen, John, 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Kang, Yeon-Mi, 1999-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Kao, Joana, 1996-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Kusumoto, Mariko, 1994-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Kranitzky, Robin and Kim Overstreet; Lost and Found, 1988-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Lewis, Keith, 1994-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Lewis, Lewis, Photographic Materials, circa 1990s-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
  - Lewis, Keith, Printed Material, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lillie, Jacqueline, circa 1999-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Mann, Thomas, Interviewed by Jill Henry for "State of the Arts," KUSP-FM, August 1988; Archival Resource Key; 1 Cassette tape (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mann, Thomas, "Techno-Romantic Jewelry Objects"; Installation, Slide Lecture, and Studio Tour, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Metcalf, Bruce, 1989-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
  - Metcalf, Bruce, Photographic Materials, 1990s-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Metcalf, Bruce, Photographic Materials, 1990s-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Metcalf, Bruce, Printed Material, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mitchell, Valerie, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
  - Miro, Darcy, circa 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Nahser, Heidi, 1990s-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Plassman, Elke, 1999-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
    File includes 2 CDs.
  - Raible, Kent, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
  - Rath, Tina, 1999-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
    File includes one CD.
  - Ross, D.X., 1991-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Russmeyer, Axel, 1995-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Rydmark, Cheryl, 1995-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Schwarcz, June, 1991-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Schwarcz, June, Photographic Materials, 1989-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17-19)
  - Schwarcz, June, Printed Material, 1990s-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Scott, Joyce, 1994-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
  - Scott, Joyce, Printed Material, 1990s-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6-9)
  - Shaw, Samuel, 1994-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Sherman, Sandra, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Slemmons, Kiff, 1987-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Slemmons, Kiff, Photographic Materials, 1990s-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13-15)
  - Slemmons, Kiff, Printed Material, 1992-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
  - Suydam, Didi, 1988-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Trask, Jennifer, 2000-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - White, Heather, 1998-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Windels, Martina, 1994-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Williamson, Roberta, 1989-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - Williamson, Roberta, Printed Material, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5-6)